<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="2010_07_13_EST A.css" type="text/css" charset="UTF-8"?>
<XML>
<TITLE> </TITLE><Hansard-Date-Heading>
<A ID="pgfId-998290"></A>
Tuesday, 13 July 2010<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-1.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
</Hansard-Date-Heading>
<LegAssembly>
<A ID="pgfId-1001385"></A>
Legislative Assembly</LegAssembly>
<Hansard-Level-1-Heading>
<A ID="pgfId-1002355"></A>
Estimates Committee A--Legislative Assembly</Hansard-Level-1-Heading>
<Hansard-Level-2-Heading>
<A ID="pgfId-1002356"></A>
Estimate Committee A Members</Hansard-Level-2-Heading>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002357"></A>
Mr SD Finn (Chair)</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002358"></A>
Mr MW Choi</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002359"></A>
Mr PA Hoolihan</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002360"></A>
Mr J-P H Langbroek</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002361"></A>
Mr TJ Nicholls</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002363"></A>
Mrs JA Stuckey</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002420"></A>
Mr WE Wendt</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Divider>
<A ID="pgfId-1002364"></A>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-1.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
</Hansard-Divider>
<Hansard-Level-2-Heading>
<A ID="pgfId-1002365"></A>
In Attendance</Hansard-Level-2-Heading>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002366"></A>
Hon. RJ Mickel, Speaker</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002367"></A>
Mr N Laurie, Clerk of the Parliament</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002368"></A>
Mr M Ries, Deputy Clerk</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002369"></A>
Mr M Hickey, Director of Corporate and House Services</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002370"></A>
Mr C Atkinson, Manager, Financial and Administrative Services</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Divider>
<A ID="pgfId-1002371"></A>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-1.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
</Hansard-Divider>
<LegAssembly>
<A ID="pgfId-1001386"></A>
Estimates Committee A--Legislative Assembly (Proof)</LegAssembly>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-2.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998303"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
Committee met at 8.30 am</Hansard-Bold>
</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998313"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 Thank you and good morning, Mr Speaker. I declare this meeting of Estimates Committee A now open. I would like to start by acknowledging the traditional owners of the land on which this hearing is taking place today. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998360"></A>
My name is Simon Finn. I am the member for Yeerongpilly and chair of the committee. Joining me on the committee today are: Michael Choi, the member of Capalaba; Paul Hoolihan, the member for Keppel; John-Paul Langbroek, the member for Surfers Paradise and deputy chair; Tim Nicholls, the member for Clayfield; Jann Stuckey, the member for Currumbin; and Wayne Wendt, the member for Ipswich West. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998415"></A>
The committee will examine proposed expenditure contained in the Appropriation (Parliament) Bill 2010 for the Legislative Assembly and the Appropriation Bill 2010 for portfolios of the Premier and Minister for the Arts, the Treasurer and Minister for Employment and Economic Development, and the Minister for Public Works and Information and Communication Technology. We will examine the estimates in that order.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998465"></A>
The proceedings today are lawful proceedings subject to the standing rules and orders of the parliament. As such, I remind all visitors that any person admitted to this hearing may be excluded in accordance with standing order 206. In relation to media coverage of the hearing, the committee has resolved to allow television coverage and photography during my introduction and the opening statements by Mr Speaker and ministers. The committee has also agreed to the live broadcast of the hearing via the Parliamentary Service’s website and to receivers throughout the parliamentary precinct. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998561"></A>
Before we begin, I would ask that mobile phones be switched off. I note at the opening of proceedings today that there is some computer equipment in the room that has not been in the room previously, including some printers. I note for members of the committee that I am happy for the printers to be here but if they create a noise that disrupts the proceedings of the committee then I will ask that they not be used. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998640"></A>
The first item for consideration in this estimates hearing is the estimates for the Legislative Assembly. I welcome you, Mr Speaker, parliamentary staff and advisers. We will examine estimates for the Legislative Assembly until 9.30 am. The time limit for questions is one minute and for answers it is three minutes. A warning bell will chime 15 seconds before the time runs out. An extension of time may be given with the consent of the questioner. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998724"></A>
For the benefit of Hansard, I ask that if advisers are called to give an answer they state their name before speaking. I now declare the propose expenditure for the Legislative Assembly open for examination. The question before the committee is--</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body-Small-Font>
<A ID="pgfId-998770"></A>
That the proposed expenditure be agreed to. </Hansard-Body-Small-Font>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998787"></A>
Mr Speaker, would you like to make an opening statement? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998807"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you, Mr Chairman. I wish to highlight how the hearings of the various estimates committees, which commence today and will proceed over the course of this week and next week, demonstrate the parliament undertaking one of its primary roles--that is, providing an opportunity for the government to be accountable and for this parliament in this session to be accountable. Though we are not meeting in the Legislative Assembly chamber, the Assembly is very much in session; it is in committee. These estimates committees are, in fact, very much the same as the committee stage of a bill being considered by the parliament in the normal course of events. In due course, the reports of the seven estimates committees of their consideration of the two appropriation bills and the expenditure they provide for will be debated in the Legislative Assembly chamber by the House as a whole. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998821"></A>
I mention these procedural aspects of the hearings of the estimates committees for a number of reasons: firstly, to highlight how they represent the parliament in action discharging its role of providing for accountable government; secondly, to highlight the fundamental importance of the parliament’s committees--currently they are under review; and, thirdly, to highlight how this kind of formal consideration of the business of the House outside the actual Legislative Assembly can and does happen successfully and provides the basis for its wider application. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998832"></A>
It is 12 months ago to the day that I first appeared before this estimates committee as Speaker, responsible for the budget estimates for the parliament. I again feel honoured to appear before the committee today. Over that 12 months it has been reinforced to me repeatedly, and I appreciate to a much greater degree, the important role that the parliament plays in our democratic system of government and the paramount importance of the funding proposed to be made available through the Appropriation (Parliament) Bill, which enables the parliament to perform its role on behalf of the people of Queensland. The spending of all public money is an important and serious matter, and I want to assure the people--the taxpayers who provide the money--that it is being spent prudently and properly and that they are getting value for money in terms of the services provided. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001228"></A>
The year just completed was one of achievement and consolidation for the parliament and the Parliamentary Service. The standout achievement, of course, was the 150th anniversary of parliament’s first sitting on 22 May 1860. One hundred and fifty years of unbroken democracy is a significant milestone for our state. There are relatively few places around the world where that has been the case.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998854"></A>
Setting the scene for the various P150 events in May was the launch in April here in this chamber of the Parliament House Conservation Plan. The plan not only documents what we have by way of buildings and contents and other assets; it also provides the blueprint for the parliament to conserve and protect the building, contents and other assets into the future. This chamber provides an example of how the plan will shape the way things are done. The large and extremely heavy centre table, for instance--a piece of heritage furniture dating from the very beginning of the parliament--has routinely been removed to make way for activities here in the chamber such as estimates hearings, increasing the risk of damaging not only the table but also other features and fittings of the chamber each time it is moved. From now on, that will happen only where it is absolutely necessary. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998863"></A>
Other achievements I should mention include finalisation of the security upgrade for electorate offices, a matter raised at last year’s hearing and, in keeping with an undertaking I gave at the time, one on which I have kept all sides regularly informed. Further information is provided in answer to one of the questions on notice. There has also been important initial work done on a strategic review of the parliament’s buildings in terms of their management and maintenance, their fitness for purpose and their compliance with relevant building codes and related requirements. Several reports have been produced and over the coming year recommendations arising out of this review as well as the conservation plan will begin to be implemented.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998876"></A>
In all it has been a blended year--a blend of the old and the new, a blend of doing the same things the same way because experience has shown that it is the best way, of doing some other things in a different way because there is a better way involved, and also of doing new things altogether. Examples are the inaugural multifaith service we had in this chamber last December and the first two citizenship ceremonies ever held here at the parliament--one last December on Proclamation Day, 10 December, and the other just last month on Queensland Day, 6 June--again, both right here in this chamber.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998889"></A>
I take this opportunity to acknowledge both sides of the House and members individually for their support and cooperation in matters relating to the functioning of the parliament, both inside and outside the chamber. I remain cognisant of the need to consult with and receive input from members generally on matters affecting them and the operation of their place of work, which encompasses not just the actual Legislative Assembly but also the parliamentary precinct and members’ electorate offices. Mr Chairman, I wish the committee well in its deliberations. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998900"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 With the conclusion of those opening remarks, I would ask that the media now leave the room. I now call the member for Surfers Paradise to begin questioning. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-998938"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Welcome Mr Speaker, and members of the Parliamentary Service. I refer to page 4-3 of the Service Delivery Statements. Under the section ‘Strategic direction’, at dot point 2 it mentions that you are going to continue to develop strategies for the parliament to engage with the community of Queensland. Part of that engagement is to ensure that Queenslanders can freely, safely and confidently raise issues with their member of parliament. You, of course, would be aware of reports where it is claimed that the member for Mount Isa received a complaint from a constituent relating to Labor’s privatisation plans. The member for Mount Isa then supposedly sent that verbatim complaint to the constituent’s employer. This is not about appropriate computer use. I would like to know what guidelines are in place that guarantee a constituent’s privacy when they write to an MP. Was the member for Mount Isa entitled to refer a verbatim complaint from a constituent back to the constituent’s employer? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-999087"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 In answer to the honourable member, I am aware of media reports regarding the member for Mount Isa and an alleged inappropriate use of resources in relation to emails. I am aware that the Parliamentary Service has a policy in place governing the use of information communication technology, including the use of emails. Generally this policy applies to staff and members. However, there are certain exemptions in place for members. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-999161"></A>
As I understand this, the allegations have been referred to the Crime and Misconduct Commission. Accordingly, I do not believe it is appropriate for me to comment at this stage, particularly as I have not been formally presented with any allegations to investigate. I will be happy to cooperate with any investigation where it is appropriate. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-999223"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
<Hansard-Bold>
 </Hansard-Bold>
I do not see that the CMC is necessarily the appropriate agency to investigate this. My question to you, Mr Speaker, is: are there guidelines that stop an MP seeking retribution against a constituent who writes with a concern? When we are new members we all get a handbook about ethical issues for members of parliament. Has consideration been given to whether we need to put some sort of guidelines into that for MPs to consider or do constituents write to MPs at their own risk, at the risk of losing their job? That does not seem very democratic to me.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-999325"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 The advice to me is that the Privacy Act does not and, as I understand it, has never applied to correspondence with MPs. If there is a matter of privilege involved or you think there is, I would ask you to send that to me in the formal way and I would be happy to investigate that formally. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-999388"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
<Hansard-Bold>
 </Hansard-Bold>
In your opening statement you spoke about doing things that we have either done before or improving our techniques or mechanisms for dealing with issues. This is obviously an issue that we need to deal with--that is, whether we issue ethical guidelines. One would have thought that the privacy issue and the confidentiality issue are not issues that would have to be explained to someone. I would be interested to have your response as to whether you may consider extending the ethical guidelines to new members of parliament either by direct instruction from you as the Speaker or via the Clerk in terms of the orientation process that we all go through. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-999493"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 My answer to the honourable member would be this. If the honourable member has a concern in relation to this--I am not cognisant of all the facts. I am aware only of a media report; I think it was in the <Hansard-Italic>
Sunday Mail</Hansard-Italic>
. I have had no material presented to me as a member or indeed as Speaker. If the honourable member feels that there is a further matter to come before and to be considered by the Integrity, Ethics and Parliamentary Privileges Committee then I think it would be better that the issue were tested in that forum. I say this: I would not want to see MPs constricted by unintended consequences with their correspondence. If this is a matter of such moment then I would prefer that that be sent to me and I will send it on to the committee for you. Over and above that, we do have the code of ethical standards and training for new MPs.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001394"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 That is right, Mr Speaker. I understand that you may not have heard my question there, because I am happy to get off the specific issue here and ask whether you may now--not necessarily in this case, but given that we have now seen apparently an unprecedented case of something that one would have expected would not have been dealt with in the way that it was--consider as part of our induction course for MPs some sort of revision or some sort of addition to the code of ethical standards that we provide for new MPs.</Hansard-Body>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-3.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001397"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 The issue for me is simply this: I honestly do not know the facts in relation to this.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001398"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I am not speaking about this case, Mr Speaker. I would presume you would say that of course we need to consider it in the light of any information that comes to hand and that we may well consider the code of ethical standards.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001399"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 The committee of itself can, as I understand it, have a look at these issues, and I would welcome it having a look at that. As I say, I would rather be in full possession of the facts here. I do not know the mitigating circumstances of the woman in relation to her contact with the member. I am only going on what I have been told was in the <Hansard-Italic>
Sunday Mail</Hansard-Italic>
.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001400"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you, Mr Speaker. Can you outline what is your understanding of what constitutes an independent officer of this parliament?</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001401"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 I just want to remind the member that we are examining the appropriation, so I would ask for a reference to the appropriation in our questioning so that we can put this in terms of the scrutiny of the appropriation.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001402"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Certainly, Mr Chairman.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001403"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 Is there a reference to the--</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001405"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Sorry, but it is part of the functions of the role of the Speaker.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001406"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I am quite happy to answer that. I think it is a perfectly legitimate question.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001407"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 Sorry, I was not trying to rule the question out of order. Just for the benefit of questioning, we need to make reference to the appropriation.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001408"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 And I am quite happy to take it because I understand there are some issues in and around this. I think I will attack it this way in terms of an officer of parliament. Section 6, for example, of the Integrity Act 2009 provides that an Integrity Commissioner is an independent officer of the parliament. However, the Integrity Commissioner has this description in common with a number of other officers. For example, section 123 of the Right to Information Act 2009 provides that the Information Commissioner is an officer of the parliament. Section 11 of the Ombudsman Act provides that the Ombudsman is an officer of the parliament. The Auditor-General is regarded as an officer of the parliament, although not expressly stated to be so in the Auditor-General Act 2009. This is the difference: none of the above officers, however--none of them--are officers of the Parliamentary Service. Because they are not officers of the Parliamentary Service, I am not responsible for their appointment or the administration of their offices or other resources. They are to be contrasted, for example, with the Parliamentary Crime and Misconduct Commissioner, who is an officer of the parliament and appointed by the Speaker as an officer of the Parliamentary Service under the Parliamentary Service Act 1988. As an officer of the Parliamentary Service I am responsible for the resources, including accommodation, of the Parliamentary Crime and Misconduct Commissioner. So I am drawing that distinction.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001417"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Mr Speaker, ‘Goals of the Parliamentary Service’ dot point 1 is to assist the parliament, its committees and members to fulfil their parliamentary responsibilities. In line with the reforms that you have brought about over the past year and given the report by the then Members’ Ethics and Parliamentary Privileges Committee report No. 89 that criticised the Treasurer’s failure to give a complete answer to questions on notice, will you outline what level of compliance you would like to see by ministers in answering questions on notice?</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001419"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I think the question is in two parts. Firstly, for questions on notice I have ensured that the 30-day rule is complied with for questions on notice. Secondly, as per rulings given down through the years, the way the question is answered is completely up to the minister.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001421"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 As per the standing orders?</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001423"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 As per the standing orders. One thing I want to emphasise with you is that we have been insistent upon the 30-day rule applying.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001424"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Mr Speaker, you and I have had discussions before about our art collection here at parliament. I know we have had meetings with the Art Gallery. Can you advise us about the current holdings and how the collection is being preserved and expanded?</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001427"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I will start it off. It has been a sense of enormous frustration, and I do thank the Leader of the Opposition for his advice and for his understanding on a frustration we both share in trying to get the artwork here upgraded. I have, in view of the heritage plan, asked that the artwork that was donated by councils be moved from this building--this heritage building--to another building. We are also engaged in an asset audit to see what artwork we have here. I might ask the Clerk to finish off my answer in relation to this.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001430"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
Mr Laurie:</Hansard-Bold>
 Mr Langbroek, just recently as part of the Speaker’s review of the artwork within the precinct what we have done is gone back into the parliamentary archives to determine the artwork that was provided to the parliament during the course of the restoration of the building in the late 1970s and the building of the Parliamentary Annexe in the 1980s when there was a significant body of artwork that was donated by local councils. Currently that artwork is spread throughout both the Parliamentary Annexe and the parliament building here. We believe it was the intention that that artwork would be essentially for the new building--that is, the Parliamentary Annexe. From the archives we have identified where each item of artwork has come from. We have also discovered correspondence between the councils and the then buildings restoration committee, I think it was called or something of that name, whereby the councils actually provided some details on the artwork when they were providing it.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001432"></A>
What we hope to do is identify each of those items of artwork, which are all here. They will go back over to the Annexe as a first step. Not only will they be placed in the Annexe where they were meant to be originally, but we anticipate that we will have an explanation with each piece of artwork explaining exactly where the artwork is from and explaining something about the artwork. In relation to artwork in the old House in particular, I do point out that part of the conservation plan was also about its contents as well as the building itself, which included artwork. As part of that conservation plan and as part of the project of the conservation plan, we are going to identify artwork that relates to this building to try to organise it in a logical sequence so that matters that pertain to the same thing are in the same area, once again with full explanations.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001434"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you. Mr Speaker, you and I have obviously discussed the acquisition of new works and what we might aim for in the new building obviously--not in the heritage part of the building--in terms of what the aims might be of the art collection, whether we want to make it a Queensland artist or whether they, as you and I have discussed but not most recently, might be just works that we might borrow from the Art Gallery that are of prominent Australian artists. Do you have a view on that?</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001435"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I have a view that, in view of the frustration that we both shared with what was offered to us by way of replacement, I think we should look at over time an acquisition program. It should not be an acquisition program based on my tastes; it should be an acquisition program. I have found, frankly, the Speaker’s Advisory Committee a very good venue for making sure that issues right across the parliament are ventilated, and that would be the type of venue that I would want. If we are going to go down an acquisition program, I would want to be confident that a cross-section of members are happy with that. I just want to answer if I can your previous question by saying that one of the things that I think we have to be careful of--the heritage plan provides us with this--is the sacrileges of the past with respect to artwork, and I am thinking now of the portrait of the first Speaker, which was brutalised. It is a bad precedent to brutalise artwork of former Speakers.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001439"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Mr Speaker, with regard to some of the portraits of the premiers that we have over there compared to other parliaments, I think we should honestly be looking at those as well.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001440"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 You are quite right. There is nothing further I can add to that; you are quite right.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001441"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I am certainly happy to work with you, Mr Speaker, in a spirit of--</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001442"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I appreciate that. The other thing that I think needs to be done with a lot of the work around here is larger captions so that people can read them. As you know--and we have discussed this--I would really like with some of the presentation as you move through this building for it to be themed much better than it is. I think if you look at it as a committee, if you walk through the parliament you will see that it is quite unthemed. In fact, the Strangers Dining Room is very unthemed, even in its presentations of things that are Queensland.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001444"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thanks. Mr Speaker, I just want to go back to my question about answers to questions on notice, and this is under ‘Goals of the Parliamentary Service’ in terms of assisting members to fulfil their parliamentary responsibilities. Mr Speaker, I know that you mentioned that you have made sure that ministers respond within 30 days. As I understand it, at times questions come back as late as 7 pm on the 30th day, which of course may coincide with the end of a week in terms of the media cycle. In other words, if we in the opposition get our answers to a question on notice after 7 pm on the 30th day, it does not come through until the 31st day and I would ask again for your clarification about what the 30th day means in terms of time frame.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001447"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 What I would say in answer--and this is for the benefit of all honourable members--is if they are finding that an incident such as the one proposed in the question is occurring, then that does interfere with the privileges of a member of parliament. In terms of the 30-day rule, the office here closes at 6 pm. If the question is supposed to be in on the day and members are finding that that is being misused, then that goes to the heart of the privileges of a member of parliament and I would ask them to raise that in the appropriate forum. The Standing Orders Committee can also look at that and I think the Standing Orders Committee has been diligent this year in its meetings, either in physical meetings or by flying minutes. So there are two avenues there. If there has been an instance where the 30-day rule has been flouted, I would ask any member to raise that as a matter of privilege.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001451"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1001453"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 The time for the first block of non-government members’ questions has come to an end. There will be another opportunity at the end of the first round of government questions. Mr Speaker, in coming to government members’ questions, I note your answer to a question on notice regarding the outcomes of the electorate office security upgrade program. I am quite aware of the security upgrade program. As a local member there have been significant improvements to the physical layout and the facilities in my office, but I would particularly like to ask about the staff training program which was part of the overall security improvements. Can you advise of details of the training conducted and the feedback you have received?</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002616"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you. Prior to the security review being finalised, the Parliamentary Service developed a training course for electorate office staff. The course was developed in consultation with the staff as part of the enterprise bargaining commitments and a pilot course was held in June 2008. As part of the security review, the Queensland Police Service noted that the training course that was being developed should cover areas that the police thought needed to be addressed to improve security, particularly in managing difficult situations and clients in electorate offices. Following the completion of the security review, some modifications were made to the training course so that electorate office security was covered in more detail during the course. </Hansard-Body>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-4.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002618"></A>
The rollout commenced in June 2008 and eight training courses were conducted, the most recent course being held on 26 and 27 May 2010. A total of 193 electorate office staff have completed the course. The course consists of two days. Day 1 was dealing with challenging situations and clients, conflict resolution, building and maintaining resilient relationships, withdrawing from aggressive client scenarios and managing emotional responses to challenging situations. I might say that that whole issue of dealing with challenging clients seems to be one that is on the rise and seems to be on the rise right across the jurisdictions, and I think that is regrettable.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002619"></A>
On day 2 of the program a variety of security and non-security topics were covered, including electorate office security systems, security resources, reporting security incidents and tips on personal security. They were delivered--and I thank them for this--by the Queensland Police Service. The non-security topics were information privacy, cultural competency training, superannuation, library resources and manual handling in the workplace. I am told that the feedback was positive for the overall training course. I really do think it is essential that our electorate staff, who serve us so well in our absence, are given the appropriate training. As I said, most of the first day was given over to training, particularly in dealing with challenging constituents or challenging situations. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002620"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr CHOI:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Mr Speaker, it is my understanding from your Service Delivery Statements that members’ satisfaction with the services provided by the Parliamentary Service is a key performance measure and indicator. How is this being measured and what action is taken to address any concerns expressed by a member of parliament? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002621"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 The Parliamentary Service seeks the views of members, but I also seek it in my own dealings with members. But to go to the Service Delivery Statements, on 24 November 2009 we provided a questionnaire to all members. Fifty-three responses out of 89 came back. Members were asked to rate the Parliamentary Service as very satisfactory, satisfactory and not satisfactory. Eighty-seven per cent of respondents rated it at the highest level. No respondent rated the overall service as not satisfactory. In nine of the individual activity areas, at least 80 per cent of respondents considered the standards of service to be very satisfactory. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002622"></A>
There were some areas of concern, and these concerns have been raised and received by management. For example, a number of members raised concerns regarding the healthy eating options in the various dining areas within the precinct. These issues are being addressed by discussions with the Heart Foundation and the development of a healthy eating program. Issues raised by members in relation to cleaning and general maintenance have also been noted and efforts have been made to improve service delivery, and issues concerning computer equipment seemed to generate a lot of activity. They will be addressed with the new equipment being rolled out in the coming months. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002624"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr WENDT:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 With reference to the community engagement goal of the Parliamentary Service at page 4-2 specifically, I am particularly keen on whether you could inform the committee of any new strategies of engaging with young Queenslanders to learn more about the role and functions of this parliament. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002626"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you. I am very pleased to inform the committee that we are trialling a new initiative in the Redlands at Sheldon College. It is our hope that this activity will be a model that can be rolled out to other regions such as Toowoomba, the Sunshine Coast and the Gold Coast. Recently the principal of Sheldon College wrote to me to ask whether parliament would be prepared to conduct a youth activity at Sheldon College as part of the United Nations International Year of Youth. I wrote back suggesting that the parliament conduct a half-day youth parliament at the college in September. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002629"></A>
What I have asked them to do is not confine it to the students at Redland Bay but to take in the surrounding areas--Cleveland, Capalaba and Springwood was my recommendation--the whole idea being that if we have it at one place for one half-day we can engage the students there in regions. If the schools are happy to host that then obviously there is a huge saving to the Parliamentary Service, because we do not have to hire halls. I think the youth get a lot out of it, because they can get to see the parliament in their own area. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002630"></A>
One other thing I have proposed with that--I think so much of the youth parliament is about debate--is that they also set aside a time for questions and answers of the acting Speakers and the Speaker as to why we ruled in particular ways. So that will be a challenge for those of us who participate in that. What I want to do, too, is see if we can extend that. We found--I think it was in Townsville--that when we did a Public Service seminar there we also set aside time for a teachers seminar on teaching teachers to teach parliamentary procedure. It was extraordinarily well attended. I do not know where we are up to with that one at Sheldon College. I think Michael was getting back to me on that. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002631"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
Mr Ries:</Hansard-Bold>
 Yes.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002632"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 That is part of the template. It means that we will go to the regions and hold the youth parliament there, but what I want is for one school to host it. We will bring in youth from around that region and, provided the school is willing to host it, I think we can make more use of community engagement in that way.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002633"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr WENDT:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you, Mr Speaker. In fact, I would like to put in a bid for Ipswich and the western corridor while I have the opportunity.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002634"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 In that case, get on to a school that may want to host it and we will take it from there. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002635"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr WENDT:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002636"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I want to reassure members of the committee that it will be done in a bipartisan way. There is no attempt to show favour to one member or another. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002637"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr HOOLIHAN:</Hansard-Member-Up>
<Hansard-Bold>
 </Hansard-Bold>
In relation to a question on notice regarding the progress of the stonework restoration program, could you outline the challenges facing the completion of the program? You mentioned the Speaker’s Green area. Can you outline the implication for the Speaker’s Green during this part of the restoration?</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002639"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 This is a very important question, because I think it is fair to say that the stonework upgrade has been appreciated and it has certainly been appreciated by people who visit the precinct. The next stage of the stonework restoration--namely inside, if you like, the Speaker’s Green--is going to present us with some problems. It is simply this: it is going to, by its necessity, impinge upon part of the Speaker’s Green, which means that scaffolding will gradually move along here so the area that is set aside as the Speaker’s Green will be impinged upon. Obviously, with that sort of stonework we need cranes to come in there to lift the stones, some of which can weigh 1 tonnes. Those cranes will need to operate from within the Speaker’s Green. A decision is yet to be made as to whether a mobile crane will be used or a fixed crane structure will be required. Cranage for works in the centre tower behind me will pose particular challenges given its height. When work on the western elevation of the Alice Street wing is undertaken there will also be implications for traffic in the Annexe forecourt. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002640"></A>
Unfortunately, the combination of scaffolding and cranes in the area will impact upon the typical use of the green, including functions and events. It will not cancel them; it will just impact on them. I am eager, of course, to minimise the extent of this impact. That is why I will work in consultation with the people undertaking it, but I think what we as a Parliamentary Service have to do is keep members fully informed so that if they are planning a function, they may have to plan around it. I commend the work that has been done in restoring this magnificent building to date. I am not going to walk away from the fact that, over time, as that work moves along this building, it will become more complex with potential for a greater impact on the Speaker’s Green. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002641"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr WENDT:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I note that in your response to a question on notice regarding the Parliament House Conservation Plan you made mention of the Speaker’s Advisory Committee and you have also mentioned that again this morning. Can you outline to this committee how you see the role of your advisory committee and the part it is able to play in the overall management of the parliament and the Parliamentary Service? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002644"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Firstly, I want to place on the record my appreciation for every member who is involved in the Speaker’s Advisory Committee. I have found that a very worthwhile activity in addressing the issues that members have. Section 9 of the Parliamentary Service Act 1998 empowers me as Speaker to establish a committee of members to advise me of issues arising under that act. I set this committee up in accordance with the act, and the terms of reference are to provide me with advice on matters affecting members. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002646"></A>
The membership is made up of me as an ex officio member and the member for Cook is the deputy chair, but I am happily joined by the member for Toowoomba South, the member for Kallangur, the member for Nanango, the member for Callide and the member for Toowoomba North. The committee is supported by the Clerk as research director and Kellie as the senior research officer. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002648"></A>
The sorts of issues we have discussed over the past 12 months have been the strategic review of parliamentary buildings, the Parliament House Conservation Plan, the stonework restoration program, the electorate office security review and, I think just as importantly, the Parliament House capital works program. As I said, I want to place on record my thanks to all of the members who have been involved in that. I think they have done a wonderful job and carried out their work in the best traditions of this place. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002649"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr CHOI:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Mr Speaker, in your Service Delivery Statements, one of the goals of the Parliamentary Service is to continue to develop strategies to engage with the Queensland community, including those Queenslanders with a multicultural background. I understand that the Community Engagement unit has undertaken several activities to engage with Queensland’s culturally and linguistically diverse community. Can you advise the committee of these activities? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002650"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I thank you very much for your question. I also want to acknowledge estimates committee members who have attended the various functions that have been held here that I said in my opening statement were groundbreaking. I particularly instance the culturally and linguistically diverse community that we have here in Queensland. That is why we had the multifaith service held in the last week of the year’s parliamentary sittings. It is my intention to hold that event again. There was the introduction of citizenship ceremonies here at Parliament House. The multifaith service was conducted with an audience of more than 100 people and many members of parliament attended that. Multifaith leaders included people from the Jewish, Hindu, Daoist, Buddhist, Christian, Muslim, Sikh, and Baha’i faiths. In recognition of the difficult economic times experienced by Queenslanders in recent times, the theme for the service was Caring for our Community. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1002652"></A>
The other initiative I referred to was the introduction of citizenship ceremonies here at Parliament House. I am pleased that, in addition to Her Excellency the Governor, who attended the first ceremony, we were joined by the honourable Leader of the Opposition and ministers, and I think for the last one we also had the Police Commissioner here. Ninety-two people from 28 countries were welcomed in June of this year, and in my role as presiding officer I want to thank the federal departments for their assistance with our Parliament House committee in relation to ensuring that we could carry out that work here. As a result of these two initiatives more than 700 people have now visited Parliament House just in respect of those two events, and I hope that those people have gone away from the parliament with a view that this place is the symbol of parliamentary democracy and freedom. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003898"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr HOOLIHAN:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Could I also go to the Service Delivery Statement. In the performance statement I note that the Parliamentary Service has a number of shared services clients. Could you advise what services are provided to these external agencies? </Hansard-Body>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-5.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003899"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Since 2003 the Parliamentary Service has provided services to a number of agencies as part of the Shared Service Initiative. In 2010 services were provided to the Queensland Audit Office, the Office of the Governor, the Office of the Ombudsman and the Office of the Information Commissioner. The Queensland Audit Office is provided with certain payroll system support services--Aurion. The Office of the Governor is provided with full payroll processing services and will in 2010 be provided with a new service--financial systems support. The Financial and Administrative Services area within the Parliamentary Service will be assisting the Office of the Governor to implement the parliament’s financial management information system. The Office of the Ombudsman is also provided with full payroll processing systems, financial systems support and some information technology infrastructure support. The Office of the Information Commissioner is provided with the most comprehensive suite of services: full payroll processing services; full financial systems, accounting and budget support; and full information technology support services. I want to congratulate all the staff here within the service who are providing that service. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003900"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 I would like to make reference to the Service Delivery Statement regarding the Parliamentary Reporting Service, a service that I as a member of parliament value fairly highly to make sense of the words that I deliver in the chamber. I understand that when parliament is not sitting staff from this area undertake reporting for other clients on a fee-for-service basis. I am wondering if you can provide details of the service provided and the associated revenue.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003901"></A>
 <Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 The Parliamentary Reporting Service has an annual revenue-raising target of $25,000. The Parliamentary Reporting Service on a fee-for-service basis assists other parliaments, such as the Commonwealth parliament and the Tasmanian parliament, to transcribe hearings of estimates committees via the internet. Subject to the sittings of the Queensland parliament, this transcription work is undertaken in February, May, July and October. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003902"></A>
The Parliamentary Reporting Service also provides fee-for-service transcription services for events held by Queensland government departments, for example the Reef Summit and the Cyclone Preparedness Summit which were held in the 2008-09 financial year. For the 2009-10 financial year, the reporting service’s fee-for-service work included the transcription of sound files for Commonwealth estimates hearings and the transcription of the Climate Change Summit for the Department of the Premier and Cabinet in October 2009. In addition, during 2010 the reporting service transcribed sound files for Tasmanian estimates hearings. The Parliamentary Reporting Service exceeded its revenue-raising target for the 2009-10 financial year, with total earned revenue of $26,500. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003903"></A>
Could I just clarify an answer to the earlier question raised by the honourable Leader of the Opposition. The standing orders are silent on the time that answers have to be recorded on the due date. Answers received prior to the close of business are always processed on the date received. Answers received after the closure of business are processed the next working day. That is when they come in by email. The issue of answers being received after close of business has not been raised as a matter of privilege in recent times. The matter was raised in the Standing Orders Committee to place a time limit on the due date, but it was not progressed. Thank you for that indulgence, Mr Chair. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003904"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR: </Hansard-Bold>
We have about 13 minutes left, so we will put eight minutes on the clock for non-government questions. I call the member for Surfers Paradise. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003905"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I want to come back to a question that I asked in the first section of non-government questions. I asked about independent officers of the parliament. I suppose this is under ‘Strategic Issues’ or ‘Departmental Services’. On his website the Integrity Commissioner states that he is an independent officer of parliament. I acknowledge that you said in your first answer that he is not part of the Parliamentary Service as defined--that he is not under your financial control as Speaker and neither are his activities. But I am interested, given that the word ‘parliament’ is part of his title on his website, in a clarification from you about your understanding of the term as per the Westminster understanding of that term. I do not recall this parliament or any parliamentary committee appointing the current Integrity Commissioner. Therefore, is he an independent officer of this parliament? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003906"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 As I understand it, the Integrity Commissioner is responsible for providing advice on integrity and ethics issues and maintaining the lobbyist register. Under the Integrity Act he can give written advice to ministers, MPs, senior public servants and others about ethics or integrity, including conflicts of interest. He may also meet with and give advice to MPs on ethics and integrity issues in relation to their declaration of interests. The Clerk, as registrar, provides advice to members as to what matters are required to be declared and the Integrity Commissioner is responsible for maintaining the lobbyist register and monitoring compliance by lobbyists and government with the act. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003907"></A>
The commissioner is appointed by the Governor in Council after there has been an advertising process and consultation with the Integrity, Ethics and Parliamentary Privileges Committee. The commissioner produces reports for the Speaker and the committee. But the Integrity Act does not provide that the Integrity Commissioner is an independent officer of the Queensland parliament. I certainly do not appoint him in the same way as the Parliamentary Service appoints other officers. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003908"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Can I ask for clarification? You just said that he is not an independent officer of the parliament. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003909"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
Mr Laurie:</Hansard-Bold>
 If I may, Mr Chair, my recollection is that the act that establishes the Integrity Commissioner does say that he is an independent officer of the parliament. That is what the act actually provides. The point Mr Speaker is making is that he is different, for example, from the office of the Parliamentary Crime and Misconduct Commissioner because the Crime and Misconduct Commissioner is appointed by the Speaker on the recommendation of the committee whereas the Integrity Commissioner, in common with the Ombudsman and other officers such as the Auditor-General et cetera, is appointed by the Governor in Council, obviously on the recommendation of the government, after consultation with the committee. I understand that in the act that was passed by the parliament there were some transitional provisions in relation to the current Integrity Commissioner because he had been appointed prior to the passage of that act. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003910"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Can I come to a couple of answers to questions on notice. In answer to question on notice No. 6, which was about the location of regional parliament, where I asked about the location of regional parliament and the ability of the Office of the Leader of the Opposition to erect information booths, in section A you said--</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body-Small-Font>
<A ID="pgfId-1003911"></A>
Should the Leader of the Opposition seek bipartisan input into future decisions he should raise the matter with the Premier. </Hansard-Body-Small-Font>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003912"></A>
Given that Mackay will host our next regional parliament--and we are all looking forward to going to Mackay, as we have been in the past to other regions of Queensland--and that is clearly a parliamentary precinct that comes under your auspices, my question is why the Leader of the Opposition should be seeking bipartisan input into decisions where clearly you as the Speaker have jurisdiction.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003913"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 The answer to the question is in a couple of parts. The precinct will be determined by the government. Once the precinct is determined, that comes under my jurisdiction. It is like the precinct of this parliament. Accordingly, once the precinct is determined I will ensure that the dignity of the parliament is maintained. As I understand it, though, if there is an area outside that precinct where information booths or whatever want to be established then that would be a matter for you and the Premier to work out. But once it comes within the precinct as determined I will work that out. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003914"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr LANGBROEK:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Thank you. The answer to question on notice No. 2 was about security measures. I see that we have had over 76,000 visitors to the precinct and, of course, I join with you in welcoming them and opening the parliamentary precinct and the parliament itself to Queenslanders. We have had even more contractors. I see that we have had 122 confiscated items. My question is about security reviews in this day and age of our security awareness being heightened. Can you tell me about what reviews have been conducted and what increased security measures have been implemented or upgraded in the parliamentary precinct or are intended to be? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003915"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I do thank you for putting the visitation in context. There have been 76,000 people visit, which is a lot of people. You are quite right: there is a review being undertaken. Each year the executive management group arranges for at least one service area within the parliamentary precinct to be reviewed. The purpose of these reviews is to ensure ongoing efficiency. A review of the Security and Attendant Service will be conducted this year. That review will be conducted in-house by the Deputy Clerk and an officer from Human Resource Management. The Deputy Clerk and the senior human resource officer are sufficiently experienced to conduct the review. I note, however, that an external consultant was engaged during the preliminary stage of the review to expertly test the validity of the physical security practices and procedures on the precinct. The first phase of the review was the physical security testing which took place in the May sittings of the parliament with a report received in June. The methodology and terms of reference for the second phase of the review were circulated for comment in June and July, with stakeholder interviews to commence in July. A final report is anticipated in September. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003916"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 That concludes the time for non-government questions. According to the clock we have time for one more government question. I know that the member for Capalaba has a question. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003917"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr CHOI:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 Mr Speaker, in relation to your answer to a question on notice regarding activities associated with the 150th anniversary of the first sitting of this parliament, can you provide more information about the open day held here on 22 May this year? </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003918"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 I certainly can. The parliament was thrown open to the people to visit on 22 May, which was exactly 150 years after the first parliament met. More than 2,000 people visited parliament. They were able to take a behind-the-scenes tour of the parliament and enjoy free live entertainment. The tour included parts of the building not usually open to the public, including a glimpse of the secret staircase and various reception rooms. I believe visitors were particularly interested in the role of Hansard and viewing the real-time machine shorthand demonstrations by the parliamentary reporters. Visitors also learned about the art of stonemasonry from the stonemasons. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003919"></A>
Among the visitors were 100 people from Queensland’s deaf community who enjoyed a special guided tour that was interpreted in Auslan. I had the privilege of meeting with them on the veranda outside. One special visitor I had the privilege of meeting with was a descendant of parliament’s first Speaker. Mr Gilbert Oakes travelled all the way from Warwick to honour his great-great-grandfather, the first Speaker, Mr Gilbert Eliott. I did not tell him about the painting. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1003920"></A>
The open day commenced with the unveiling of the P150 legacy project, the Speakers Corner, which will be similar to the famous Speakers Corner in London’s Hyde Park--only, unlike at the House of Commons, our Speakers Corner will be right outside the parliament, a designated area marked out in front of Parliament House. I want to thank also the council for not going ahead with what would have been a huge interference with that, and I want to thank Jane Prentice for her work with that.</Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1005148"></A>
I want to thank also Her Excellency the Governor and other members of parliament who were available on that day to launch that. Adding to the ceremony of the unveiling were Auntie Carol Curry from the Brisbane Council of Elders, the Australian Army Band of Brisbane and the city of Ipswich town crier, Mr Mark Overell. He made a substantial contribution to the proceedings on the day by composing and delivering a special cry for the launch of the new Speaker’s Corner and later donated his time to work with us as a master of ceremonies. I know the member for Ipswich West would probably know Mark. I ask if he can convey our thanks to him. </Hansard-Body>
<DIV>
<IMAGE xml:link="simple" href="2010_07_13_EST A-6.gif" show="embed" actuate="auto"/>
</DIV>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1005157"></A>
Other visitors included the Australian Army Band Brisbane, the Australian Army Band Brisbane Jazz Ensemble, the Brisbane River City Clippers, the Bollywood Dhamaka, the Jaran Aboriginal Dance Troupe and the inspirational choir the Transformers. Free activities were also provided for children including face painting and there was the educational One Punch Can Kill display and a free sausage sizzle. I also want to acknowledge the fact that the Queensland division of the Royal Flying Doctor Service was here as were the representatives of Foodbank, who do such a wonderful job. They made this day especially memorable. Above all, I want to thank particularly the Parliamentary Service staff who volunteered to work on this special day and made it, I think, a huge success. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1005166"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 Thank you, Mr Speaker. The time allotted for consideration of the proposed expenditure for the Legislative Assembly has now come to a close. I know over the years it has been very clear to me the amount of work that your office and the advisers and officers of the parliament put into this estimates committee process. I would like to thank you all for your participation in the scrutiny today. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1005167"></A>
<Hansard-Member-Up>
Mr SPEAKER:</Hansard-Member-Up>
 May I thank you and the committee for your courtesy today. I would hope that the committee would also thank the officers within the parliamentary precinct, both for preparing all the answers, which I hope I have delivered to the committee in the style in which they presented them, but also for the diligence and the courtesy they extend to me in my job and I think to each and every member of parliament and also to the visiting public. So on my behalf, thank you very much for what you do. Have a great day with the committee. I am sure the rest of the day will not be as controversial as this session has been. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1005168"></A>
<Hansard-Bold>
CHAIR:</Hansard-Bold>
 Thank you. On that note, could I ask that the changeover happen efficiently and rapidly as we do have a long day on this committee. </Hansard-Body>
<Hansard-Body>
<A ID="pgfId-1005240"></A>
</Hansard-Body>
</XML>
